Mozambique Subject Files, Inclusive: 1973-1999, Bulk: 1976-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Mozambique Subject Files
Inclusive: 1973-1999, Bulk: 1976-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
9
Keston Institute, 1969 -
2 A4 document boxes.
The Mozambique Subject Files contain a variety of materials on the Mozambique Marxist government and its policies and practices, including human rights violations and religious persecution.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the name changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist and totalitarian countries. The Keston Archive and Library houses numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals. With materials dating from 1973 to 1999, Keston collected documents reflecting the political, as well as the religious climate of Mozambique.
Formerly a Portuguese colony, the African country of Mozambique gained its independence in 1975, coming under the rule of a single-party governmental system. The Marxist Front for the Liberation of Mozambique (FRELIMO) became the ruling party with Samora Machel as president. In response to the Communist regime, anticommunist forces raged a civil war funded by South Africa and Rhodesia, later Zimbabwe. The battle between the rebel group, the Mozambique National Resistance (RENAMO), and the Marxist government led to the displacement of approximately 4 million people. Another million individuals died of violence, famine or disease before the conflict formally ended in 1992.
Joaquim Chissano ascended to the presidency following Samora Machel’s sudden death in an airplane crash in 1986. Chissano, who served as president until 2004, abandoned Marxism in 1989. The following year, the country amended the constitution to allow multiparty elections, a free market economy, and lessening restrictions on religious groups. In 1992, during Chissano’s presidency, the government and RENAMO reached a peace agreement that ended the civil war.
Scope and Content
Mozambique Subject Files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, news reports, and newsletters. Materials cover the period from 1973-1999 with the bulk from 1976-1989. The majority pertain to the Mozambique Marxist government and its policies and practices, including human rights violations and religious persecution.
Arrangement
The Keston center received the Mozambique materials organized by categories. Within these categories, all materials were organized chronologically. This organization has mostly been preserved but has been divided further into specific thematic subjects.
The Mozambique Subject Files are currently arranged in one series: I. General.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 9.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Machel, Samora, 1933-1986.
Subjects (Organizations)
FRELIMO (Organization); Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.; RENAMO (Organization)
Places
Mozambique -- Economic conditions -- 1975-; Mozambique -- Foreign relations.; Mozambique -- History -- 1994-; Mozambique -- History -- Independence and Civil War, 1975-1994.; Mozambique -- Politics and government -- 1975-1994.; Mozambique -- Politics and government -- 1994-; Mozambique -- Religion.; Wiriyamu (Mozambique) -- Massacre, 1972.
Subjects
Civil rights and socialism -- Mozambique.; Communism -- Mozambique.; Decommunization -- Mozambique.; Economic assistance -- Mozambique.; Freedom of religion -- Mozambique.; Human rights -- Mozambique.; Humanitarian assistance -- Mozambique.; Persecution -- Mozambique.; Poverty -- Mozambique.; Religion and state -- Mozambique.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.)
- General, 1973-1999; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Scope and Content
  Mozambique General Subject Files contain information on the Mozambique Marxist government, including President Samora Machel, elections, and resistance. Additionally, there are documents pertaining to Mozambique’s international relations with nations such as Portugal, the Soviet Union, South Africa, Zimbabwe and other African nations.
  Documents pertaining to issues of religion highlight the oppression of the Catholic and Anglican churches, Machel’s “war on the church,” external pressure for freedom of religion, and missionary activities. There are individual folders for the following denominations: Anglican, Islam, Lutheran, and Roman Catholic.
  - General, 1976-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Individuals. Machel, Samora, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Government, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Elections, 1983-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mozambican National Resistance (RENAMO), 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mozambican National Resistance (RENAMO), 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Massacres, 1973-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Emigration and Refugees, 1976-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Constitution, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Church and State, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Church and State, 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Basic Rights and Freedoms, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Law, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Prisons and Labor Camps, 1976-1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Imprisonment and Prisoners, 1977-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Executions, 1980-1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - International Relations, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - International Relations. Malawi, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - International Relations. Portugal, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - International Relations. South Africa, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - International Relations. Soviet Union, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - International Relations. United Kingdom, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - International Relations. United States, 1978-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - International Relations. Zimbabwe, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Humanitarian Aid, 1976-1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Defections, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Religion. General, 1975-1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Missionaries, 1975-1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Religious Individuals. Campos, Martinho, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Religious Individuals. Mahlalela, Isaac, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bibles, 1976-1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Opening, Closing, Demolition, and Return of Religious Property, 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive Practices Relating to Religious Activity, 1975-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Imprisonment, 1976-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Anglican Church, 1975-1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Islam, 1976-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lutheran Church, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Roman Catholic Church, 1976-1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Church Growth and Revival, 1976-1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Religious Statistics, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Communism. Socialism, 1976-1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Agriculture and Economy, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Tourism, 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Radio. Newspaper. Broadcasting, 1977-1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Women, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)